<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Christian Ryan</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Christian Ryan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Christian Ryan 2020</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>2.4 - Sentiment analysis of dreams</title>
      <link>/2020/02/15/sentiment-analysis-of-dreams/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/15/sentiment-analysis-of-dreams/</guid>
      <description>In the last post we compared the dream sets by graphing the most frequently occurring words and calculating correlation coefficients. But in psychology, we are often interested in specific aspects of the text to analyse. From my own perspective, emotional language use is of particular interest. A further way in which we could compare the dreams is by carrying out a sentiment analysis. One could use bespoke software such as the LIWC programme (http://liwc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.3 - Using tidytext to compare samples of dreams</title>
      <link>/2020/01/27/using-tidytext-to-compare-samples-of-dreams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/27/using-tidytext-to-compare-samples-of-dreams/</guid>
      <description>This is the third post in the series exploring text analytics with data from the dreambank.com. In the first post ‘Pulling text data from the internet’, I demonstrated how to use the rvest package to pull text data from the dreambank website. In the second post ‘Manipulating text data from dreams’ we saw how to turn the dream texts into a tidy format by unnesting the word tokens in each dream and running counts on the word frequencies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.2 - Manipulating text data from dreams</title>
      <link>/2020/01/14/manipulating-text-data-from-dreams/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/14/manipulating-text-data-from-dreams/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post on ‘pulling text data from the internet’, I experimented with pulling out the dream text from a sample of dreams from the website “DreamBank” at: http://www.dreambank.net/random_sample.cgi.
In this follow-up post, I will demonstrate some of the methods presented in Julia Silge and David Robinson’s book ‘Text Mining with R’ for processing text data, as applied to 400 dreams sampled from 4 collections in the dreambank. I used the methods described in the last post to pull out a random sample of 100 dreams from each of the following 4 groups:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.1 - Pulling text data from the internet</title>
      <link>/2019/11/30/pulling-text-data-from-the-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/30/pulling-text-data-from-the-internet/</guid>
      <description>I have been working on the area of alexithymia for the last couple of years, a sub-clinical condition in which people find it difficult to identify and describe their emotions. I am currently analysing a dataset containing transcripts of interviews with people with and without alexithymia and I wanted to try out some R tools for text analysis. However, to do a blog post I needed some public data, and while mulling over which data I might use, I stumbled upon a line in “You are a thing and I love you” - the wonderful new book on AI by Janelle Shane.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1 - Plotting multiple histograms on the same graph</title>
      <link>/2019/10/12/plotting-multiple-histograms-on-the-same-graph/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/12/plotting-multiple-histograms-on-the-same-graph/</guid>
      <description>Recently, while trying to compare the distribution of two samples, I discovered that you can plot both on the same graph in base R, which is a nice feature if you just want to examine the data quickly. We can explore this with a psychological dataset from the Open Psychometrics site. This hosts a range of open psychometric tests and stores the data in an accessible form. Let’s pull out the data for the Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale (note that there are two different scoring methods in common use on this scale - on the website they have used a 1 - 4 Likert scale for the data output as a csv, but it is not unusual to see the use of a 0 - 3 scale, (which is the method used to give participants on the website feedback) so we need to be cautious when comparing these total scores with published norms (see https://socy.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>